Guide to the Donald Holcomb papers, 1952-2004
Holcomb, Donald papers, 1952-2004
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Donald Holcomb papers, 1952-2004
14-22-3426
Holcomb, Donald Frank, 1925-
7 cubic ft.
Publications, correspondence, manuscripts, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, lab notebooks, research and subject files on electron paramagnetic resonance, and experimental data pertaining to Holcomb's work at Cornell in the Dept. of Physics and in the Laboratory of Atomic and Solid State Physics.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Donald Holcomb served as Director of the Cornell Laboratory of Atomic and Solid State Physics from 1964-1968 and Chairman of the Department of Physics from 1969-1974 and 1982-1986.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, lab notebooks, research and subject files on electron paramagnetic resonance, and experimental data pertaining to Holcomb's work at Cornell in the Dept. of Physics and in the Laboratory of Atomic and Solid State Physics.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University. Dept. of Physics.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Laboratory of Atomic and Solid State Physics.
Subjects:
Physics--Study and teaching--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Electron paramagnetic resonance.; Physics.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. External to Cornell Non-Research Activities
Series II. Laboratory Notebooks
Series III. Personal Research Files
Series IV. Miscellaneous and Non-Research Activities
Series V. Miscellaneous Experimental Data, Analysis, Correspondence, Writeups, etc.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. External to Cornell Non-Research Activities
  - Various external activities (mostly physics education or AAPT-based; more in Box #2), 1977-1996 (Box 1)
  - Education conference notes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes from various evaluation or study committees (Box 1)
  - Public lectures - AIP Visiting Scientist, IUPP, Conferences, etc. (Box 1)
  - Various external activities (mostly physics education or AAPT-based), 1996-2004 (Box 2)
  - External visiting committees - mostly physics departments of various colleges (Box 2)
  - Editorial Boards - Physical Review and Physical Review Letters (Box 2)
  - Introductory University Physics Project National development effort supported by NSF; John Rigden, original stimulator and PI of first grant, Holcomb and Larry Coleman Cop-PI's in latter stages, 1987-1995 Steering Committee Notes Some information on various course models Interactions with NSF (Box 2)
- Series II. Laboratory Notebooks
  - Personal college and grad school lab course notebooks (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous research lab notebooks from Holcomb and other workers in Holcomb Lab, 1952-1992 This assortment of lab books is very incomplete - in some cases because notebooks left Cornell with the primary contributors, in some because the notebook fit more clearly into Boxes 7 or 8. In the case of lab notebooks from Holcomb work as a graduate student at the University of Illinois, the ratio of useful material to bulk was simply too small to justify saving. This work is quite fully described in Holcomb's Ph.D. thesis, "Nuclear magnetic resonance in alkali metals," 1954. A copy of this is held in the Cornell library. (Box 3)
- Series III. Personal Research Files
  - Misc. research correspondence, 1961-1992 (Box 4)
  - Sabbatical leaves - correspondence and other information Central Institute for Industrial Research, Oslo, 1962 University of Kent, Canterbury, UK, 1968-1969 University of St. Andrews, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Notes from research conferences Metal-Insulator Transitions - San Francisco, 1968 Metal-Insulator Transitions - Aussois, France, 1971 International Conference on Physics of Semiconductors - Stuttgart, 1974 International Conference on Physics of Semiconductors - San Francisco, 1984 International Conference on Physics of Semiconductors - Stockholm, 1986 Mid-Winter Solid State Conference - Laguna Beach, CA, 1977 Scottish Universities Summer School in Physics - St. Andrews, 1978 and 1986 IBM - Heavy doping and the M-I transition in semiconductors - Santa Cruz, CA, 1984 "Localization 1999" - Hamburg, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Research-based public lectures, 1953-2003 (Box 4)
  - Research grant information ONR, 1959-1969 Materials Science Center, 1960-1984 Army Research Office - Durham, 1965-1972 National Science Foundation, 1972-1977, 1980-1991 (Box 4)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous and Non-Research Activities
  - Misc. non-research correspondence, 1954-1992 (Box 5)
  - Notes from various internal to Cornell activities (Box 5)
  - Notes from preparation of My Father's Watch: Aspects of the Physical World, with Philip Morrison, 1968-1973 (Box 5)
  - Holcomb's running notebooks of non-research activities (Cornell-based and various external education oriented activities) 1971-2002 (Box 5)
- Series V. Miscellaneous Experimental Data, Analysis, Correspondence, Writeups, etc.
  - NMR in Alkali Metals from Illinois with R. E. Norberg, 1952-1955 (Box 7)
  - NMR in Alkali Metals from Cornell, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - F-centers in BaO, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Double resonance in Al metal (Box 7)
  - Correspondence with Tomita, Redfield, etc. (Box 7)
  - Sliker info on ESR of impurities AgCl (Box 7)
  - F-center relaxation times in KCl - W. D. Ohlsen, 1962 (Box 7)
  - F-centers in NaF, 1962 (Box 7)
  - NMR of Pb in glass - J. H. Strange, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Hydrate crystals - McGrath and Silvidi, gypsum, etc. - Pedersen data, 1960-1962 (Box 7)
  - Semiconductors (work of R. K. Sundfors, Jack Kaeck, Gary Carver, M. Iwasawa, Gifford Irown), 1962-1974 (Box 7)
  - Silicon Carbide - M. Alexander, 1966 (Box 7)
  - Data and Analysis in NaxWO3, LixWO3, 1970-1978 and NaxTayW1-yO3, 1982-1986 Work of Paul Lightsey, Rick Zumsteg, David Tunstall, David Lilienfeld, Bob Weinberger, Jean Dumas, Mike Dubson (Box 7)
  - Data on Alkali-graphite intercalculated materials by Gary Carver, 1969-1971 (Box 8)
  - Data, notebooks, graphs on Cu-Au and Rb-Au compounds (work of Gerard Tinelli and Wayne Phillips), 1974-1978 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous information on the second wave of major emphasis on heavily-doped Si - both singly-doped with P, As, Sb, double-doped with P and As, compensated with P and B, 1978-1992 Research planning folder, 1978-1980 Work of Paul Newman, Mark Hirsch, Uwe Thomanschefsky, Professor M. J. R Hoch of University of the Witwatersrand, undergraduates Mohan Namboodiri and Dimitry Reznik (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Andrei Zabrodskii - small Cornell conference, 1991 (Box 8)